

#### DATA SCIENCE PRACTICE LEAD & AD HINCT PROFESSOR OF DATA SCIENCE

1400 Maryland Ave. Havertown, PA 19083

□ (410) 231-9371 | ■ jacob.rozran@gmail.com | ♠ jakelearnsdatascience.com | ᡚ jrozra200 | ் jacob-rozran | У StatsManPHL

## Summary\_

In addition to being a dad, uncle, & data guy, I am a data & technology professional with real-world experience in data science, advocacy, building and growing teams, project management, sales, consulting, and teaching. I am curious about the changing landscape of technology's impact on our lives and especially passionate about fair and ethical algorithms. My passion for data and statistics has also inspired me to become an Adjunct Professor of Data Science & Statistics, which has improved my ability to explain complex subjects to all levels of understanding.

# Top Skills & Technologies

METHODS	APPLICATIONS	LANGUAGES	DATABASES
Data Visualization	RStudio	SQL	PostgreSQL
Advanced Analytics	Jupyter Notebooks	R	Hive/Impala (Hadoop)
Project Management	Tableau/Metabase/Redash	Python	Athena (AWS)
Statistical Modeling	GitHub	Bash	SQL/mySQL/SQLite
People Leadership	MS Office Suite	HTML	Neo4J

# **Experience**

**CivicActions**Lafayette, CA

DATA SCIENCE PRACTICE LEAD

Feb 2021 - Present

- Building a Data Science Practice Area with > \$1MM revenue after 12 months; personally focused on data science, people management and coaching, sales, marketing, and project management.
- For the Centers of Medicare and Medicaid (CMS), leveraging Natural Language Processing (NLP) in the creation and evaluation of System Security Plans (SSPs) to optimize the Authority to Operate (ATO) process; analyzing AWS usage to forecast annual usage and identify inefficiencies; using graph analysis and NLP to identify related documents to provide enhanced search capabilities.
- One of five members of the company's Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, and Accessibility (DEIA) team; responsible for helping improve the company's
  DEIA practices, including analyzing demographic data, designing surveys to understand company feeling about DEIA, and identifying and improving company policy to be more inclusive.

Villanova, PA

ADJUNCT PROFESSOR OF DATA SCIENCE & STATISTICS

Aug 2020 - Present

- Build the syllabus, lectures, assignments, projects, and tests for undergraduate Data Science, Intro to Statistics, and Intro to Statistics for Biology courses
- Advise and mentor students by writing recommendations for various programs, helping guide studies for real-world success after graduation, and providing assistance through the stresses of university life.

Socure New York, NY

SOLUTIONS CONSULTANT

Jan 2020 - Feb 2021

- Technical expert on fraud prevention, Know Your Customer (KYC)/Customer Identification Program (CIP), Socure product modules, data science, statistics, and data visualization in support of the sales and onboarding processes.
- Created custom proof-of-concept (POC) analyses for prospective customers showing the value of Socure versus their current solution(s).
- Served as the Growth Team's subject matter expert (SME) on data science, creating educational documents and presentations on challenging topics like Area Under the Curve (AUC), false positives, and other model evaluation criteria.
- Worked with the Marketing Team to create content for the Socure Blog on machine learning techniques.
- Member of the DEI team.

#### **Xfinity Mobile Risk Management (Comcast)**

Philadelphia, PA

MANAGER OF DATA ANALYTICS

Mar 2017 - Jan 2020

- Lead and manage the data analytics and engineering team for Xfinity Mobile Credit Risk Management, including hiring and training of staff analysts and engineers, collaborating with and providing analysis for stakeholders, and tracking and prioritizing all team tasking.
- Designed and built a fraud decision making tool that combines custom feature creation, statistical and business rules, and predictive models built in R, Python, and Bash, which, in large part, is responsible for a decrease in month-over-month fraud losses by 92% in 2018.
- · Forecast involuntary churn (both bad debt and unit loss) for the organization on the numerous segments of our customer base.
- Provide coaching, leadership, and mentorship to all analysts on the Xfinity Mobile Risk Management team.

Philadelphia, PA

Senior Data Analyst Sep 2014 - Mar 2017

- Designed and built predictive models, which improved compromised user account detection times and discovery accuracy this work was
  presented internally along with several internal blog posts about the effort.
- Used statistical methods to discover and automate the detection of anomalies.
- Created forecasts of user base growth and project completion.
- Maintained and monitored KPIs for multiple application teams within the organization.

#### **Messaging Application Engineering (Comcast)**

Philadelphia, PA

PROJECT MANAGER

Apr 2013 - Sep 2014

- Served as a Project Manager and ScrumMaster for the Messaging Application Engineering (MAE) team, responsible for Residential Voicemail
  and Email Engineering teams.
- · Obtained my Project Management Professional (PMP) and Certified ScrumMaster (CSM) certifications.
- Instituted and evangelized Scrum on both the email and voicemail teams, migrating from a hybrid of waterfall and Kanban, which led to higher team productivity, better communication across teams from development through deployment to production, and improved interaction with our product owners.
- Managed the scheduling and owned the priorities for multiple work streams and teams.

#### NCS Main Study Information Management Systems Project (Booz Allen Hamilton)

Rockville, MD

IMPLEMENTATION MANAGER

Nov 2010 - Apr 2013

- Served as the Implementation Manager and Site Administrator for the National Children's Study (NCS) Portal, a Microsoft SharePoint 2010 web application, the NCS Application Homepage, and NCS Password Self Service.
- Developed a configuration change process for the NCS Portal that streamlined the enhancement process for the site and provided the client with quicker updates while still meeting contractual and firm guidelines.

### **NAVAIR RIS Project (Booz Allen Hamilton)**

Lexington Park, MD

FINANCIAL ANALYST/PROJECT MANAGER

Nov 2009 - Oct 2010

- Developed a financial tracking system for client, which allowed key stakeholders to view current and projected funding over the lifetime of the contract.
- Tracked current funding for multiple engineers and monitored the expenditures of funds on their contracts, which ensured that projects remained on budget.

### Volunteer.

Govern for America Katonah, NY

RESIDENT DATA SCIENCE EXPERT

April 2022 - Present

Provide training and mentorship in data science, data visualization, and data ethics for GFA fellows.

**Data Jawn Conference**Philadelphia, PA

ORGANIZER

April 2019 - Present

 Assisted in promotion, speaker selection, and day-of-event logistics for the Data Jawn, a Philadelphia data conference highlighting the great work of our local data community.

#### **Montgomery County Public Defender**

Norristown, PA

DATA ANALYST

May 2016 - Jun 2017

- Assisted Montgomery County Public Defender to define an analytics strategy to support competitive salaries and fair defence for all Montgomery County residents.
- Created, built, and maintained advanced analysis.

#### Education

Villanova University Villanova, PA

MASTERS OF SCIENCE - APPLIED STATISTICS

2015 - 2017

Completed my program while working full time

Drexel University Philadelphia, PA

BACHELORS OF SCIENCE - BUSINESS & ENGINEERING

2004 - 2009

- Drexel Representative for Student Lobbying Day in Harrisburg, PA, 2009
- Drexel University Traditions Council Treasurer, 2007 2009
- Dean's List, 2006, 2008
- Drexel Representative to Colonial Athletic Association's Student Athlete Advisory Committee, 2006
- Drexel University Varsity Soccer Player, 2004 2006